<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Copyright 2019-2022 Timothy Yusun -->
<!-- This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License-->
<!-- https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0 -->

<frontmatter xml:id="front" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <titlepage>
        <author>
            <personname>TJ Yusun</personname>
            <department>Department of Mathematical and Computational Sciences</department>
            <institution>
                <line>University of Toronto Mississauga</line>
                <line>Mississauga, ON, Canada</line>
            </institution>
            <email>tj.yusun@utoronto.ca</email>
        </author>
        <date><today /></date>
    </titlepage>
   
       
    <preface xml:id="front-welcome">
        <title>Welcome Message</title>
        <p>
            <alert>September 2022</alert>
        </p>
        
        <sidebyside widths="70%">
        <image source="figs/TJ.jpg"><description>TJ posing with a "V" sign on vacation in Vietnam</description></image>
        </sidebyside>

        
        <p>
            Hello all!
        </p>

        <p>
            You can call me Professor/Prof. Yusun, Dr. Yusun, or TJ; my pronouns are he/him/his.
            I did my PhD at <url href="https://sfu.ca">Simon Fraser University</url>, in the area of operations research.
        </p>
        <p>
            The past two years have brought with it multiple challenges for students and faculty alike.
            We have all been affected in different ways by many different events since, and it is understandable that you may not be in the optimal mindset to study. 
        </p>
        
        <sidebyside widths="70%">
            <image source="figs/UTMwinter.jpg"><description>View from the third floor of Deerfield Hall on the UTM campus. Footprints on snow-covered pathways in a V shape with bare trees in the middle. </description></image>
        </sidebyside>
    
        <p>
            Things are slowly starting to move back to more familiar ground: classes will be in-person, and I hope 
            (TO BE CONTINUED)


            Regardless of what happens, whether this plan changes or not, the MAT202 teaching team would like to make a number of commitments to you:
            <ul>
                <li>In all aspects of the course, we will be clear and organized, and reduce as many barriers to your access and learning that we can.</li>
                <li>We will be reasonably available to help you with your learning.</li>
                <li>We will do my best to listen when you speak. Your voices are important to us.</li>
                <li>We will treat you with respect and dignity, and make our class a safe learning environment for you and your peers.</li>
            </ul>
            In return, all we ask is that:
            <ul>
                <li>You uphold academic integrity in everything you do.</li>
                <li>You sincerely attempt to engage actively in the course (material, classes, tutorials, and discussions) and submit assessments by their due dates.</li>
                <li>You treat your classmates, TAs and instructor with respect and dignity, and make the class a safe learning environment for everyone.</li>
                <li>You expect to make mistakes, and view them as opportunities to learn and grow.</li>
                <li>You reach out to me and communicate any thoughts or concerns you may have about the course, or anything that you want me to know.</li>
            </ul>
        </p>
        <p>
            Moreover, there <em>will</em> be technology difficulties and failures throughout the term... 
            This is to be expected, and we will manage.
            For the majority of you who took courses online last year, I also hope that you've learned a bit about yourselves<mdash/>your strengths, weaknesses, motivations, desires, and needs<mdash/>and that you are able to take these lessons with you in the new academic year.
        </p>
        <p>
            Finally, let me reiterate that <em>we want you to succeed</em>, and we will try our best to facilitate this.
            But also remember that your success depends on the actions you take. 
            We are in this together.
        </p>
        <p>
            <em>Prof. TJ Yusun</em>
        </p>
                    
    </preface>
    
 
    <preface xml:id="front-how-to-use">
        <title>About This Resource</title>
        <p>
            The word <em>discrete</em> in the title of our course means <em>separate</em>; something that is <em>not smooth</em>.
        </p>
        <p>
            In the study of discrete mathematics we will typically concern ourselves with discrete objects such as the integers, graphs, finite and countable sets. (In contrast, excluded from this are objects that may vary continuously, such as those ones covered in trigonometry, calculus, and Euclidean geometry.)
        </p>
        <p>
            In these notes we take a tour through a variety of topics including counting techniques, the pigeonhole principle, number theory, and graph theory.
            Material is presented in a manner that encourages the reader to actively engage with the material, via inline exercises (called <sq>checkpoints</sq>) scattered throughout each section.
            A number of historical explorations and asides give context to some of these topics, and hopefully allow for a critical reflection on the historical and political underpinnings of the field and of mathematics as a whole.
        </p>
        <p>
            These notes are being developed specifically for the Fall/Winter 2020-2023 offerings of MAT202: Introduction to Discrete Mathematics course at the <url href="https://www.utm.utoronto.ca/math-cs-stats/home">University of Toronto Mississauga</url>.
            For the online offering of this course a number of short videos will be produced and uploaded into the HTML version of these notes, to be inline with the text and in close proximity to the topic being discussed.
            These videos will be created and uploaded throughout the term.
        </p>
        <p>
            A PDF (with no solutions or videos) will also be posted for offline access to the notes.
            The goal is to provide students with as many means of accessing and learning the material as possible (video, audio, text) but also for these notes to represent a logical flow for the course that supports student self-study.
        </p>
        <p>
            Notable changes from the Fall/Winter 2019-2020 PDF notes include:
            <ul>
                <li>Section 1.4 removed and expanded to a new appendix on mathematical communication;</li>
                <li>A number of historical explorations added throughout the text (there are plans for more in the future);</li>
                <li>Sections 5.2 and 5.5 each split into two smaller sections; paths and connectedness defined earlier in chapter;</li>
                <li>A small number of exercises (both inline and end-of-chapter) now have solutions in the HTML version;</li>
                <li>New appendices added that index the introduction of new notation (<xref ref="app-notation"/>), list results (<xref ref="app-definitions-theorems"/>), and compile examples and exercises (<xref ref="app-explorations"/>).</li>
            </ul>
        </p>


    </preface>
    
    <preface xml:id="front-feedback">
        <title>Feedback and Acknowledgements</title>
        <p>
            <alert>Feedback</alert>
            This is an ongoing project, and so the text may contain errors or typos.
            Errata will be posted in the Quercus course container for MAT202 as they are found; minor errors not affecting the numbering of results are likely to be corrected right away in the HTML version.
            Students are encouraged to email <url href="mailto:tj.yusun@utoronto.ca?subject=202notes-pretext"><c>tj.yusun@utoronto.ca</c></url> if you find any errors or would like to provide feedback about these notes.
        </p>
        <p>
            When emailing, please include the following:
            <ul>
                <li>Description of error</li>
                <li>URL of error (if in the online version) and date found</li>
                <li>page number of error (if in the PDF version), and compile date on the front page of the pdf.</li>
            </ul>
        </p>

        <p>
            <alert>Acknowledgements</alert>
            Massive thanks to all the contributors to the <url href="https://pretextbook.org/">PreTeXt</url> system, which was used to produce HTML and PDF outputs of this work.
        </p>


<!--
        <attribution>
            <line>
                TJ Yusun
            </line>
        </attribution>
-->
    </preface>

        <colophon xml:id="colophon">

        <edition>Introduction to Discrete Mathematics: Fall/Winter 2022-2023</edition>

        <website>
            <name><c>itdm</c></name>
            <address>https://tjyusun.com/MAT202/</address>
            <!-- Update to git later -->
        </website>

        <copyright>
            <year>2019<ndash/>2022</year>
            <holder>Timothy Yusun</holder>
            <minilicense>CC-BY-NC-SA 4.0 License</minilicense>
            <shortlicense>
                This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License. You can view a copy of the license <url href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">here</url>.
            
                    <image source = "figs/by-nc-sa" width="25%"/>

            </shortlicense>
        </copyright>

        <credit>
            <role>Source files</role>
            <entity>
                Link to source will be posted here later.
                <!--
                The source files for this document can be found at <url href="https://github.com/tjyusun/itdm">this git repository</url>.
                -->
            </entity>
        </credit>

    </colophon>

</frontmatter>  



