<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- Copyright 2019-2020 Timothy Yusun -->
<!-- This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License-->
<!-- https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0 -->



<exercises xml:id="exercises-principles">
<introduction>
<p>Additional Exercises for <xref ref="chap-principles"/></p>
</introduction>

<exercise>
<statement>
	<p>
		Prove that any <m>(n+1)</m>-subset of <m>\{1,2,\ldots,2n\}</m> has a pair of consecutive numbers.
	</p>
	<p>
		Why does this imply that any <m>(n+1)</m>-subset must have a pair of relatively prime numbers?
    </p>
</statement>
<solution>
	<p>
		Define pigeonholes to be <m>\{1,2\}</m>, <m>\{3,4\}</m>, and so on.
	</p>
</solution>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
	<p>
		Prove that any <m>(2n+1)</m>-subset of <m>\{1,2,\ldots,3n\}</m> has three consecutive numbers.
	</p>
</statement>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
	<p>
		The numbers 1 to 10 are placed in some order around a circle. Prove that some set of three consecutive numbers sums to at least 17.
    </p>
</statement>
<hint>
	<p>
		What should the average of all the three-sums be?
	</p>
</hint>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
	<p>
		Jungkook has 6 friends; over several days he invites some of them over to his home to eat lamb skewers for dinner, so that the company never repeats (<ie/> a different set of friends comes every night).
		If he has at least one friend over every day, how many days can he follow this rule?
    </p>
</statement>
</exercise>
<p>
</p>

<sidebyside widths="15% 82%" margins="auto">
<image xml:id="img-php-square-2cm" halign="center">
	<description>A two by two grid.</description>
    <latex-image>
		\begin{tikzpicture}
		\draw[-,thick] (0,0)--(2,0)--(2,2)--(0,2)--(0,0);
		\draw[-,dashed] (1,0)--(1,2);
		\draw[-,dashed] (0,1)--(2,1);
		\end{tikzpicture}
	</latex-image>
</image>
<exercise>
<statement>
	<p>
		Place 5 points inside (or on the boundary) of a square with side length 2 cm. 
		Show that there is a pair of points no more than <m>\sqrt{2}</m> cm apart.
    </p>
</statement>
</exercise>
</sidebyside>

<exercise>
<statement>
	<p>
		Recall that the <term>midpoint</term> of the segment joining points <m>(a,b)</m> and <m>(c,d)</m> on the plane has coordinates <me>\left(\frac{a+c}{2},\frac{b+d}{2}\right)</me>.

		Show that given five integer points (<ie/> points with integer coordinates) on the plane, the midpoint of the segment joining some pair of them is also an integer point.
    </p>
</statement>
<hint>
	<p>
		Consider parity.	
	</p>
</hint>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
	<p>
		If we select 38 subsets of size at most three from the set <m>S = \{1,2,\ldots,13\}</m>, show that two of these subsets must have the same sum.
    </p>
</statement>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
	<p>
		The UTM e-sports team <em>Eagle Geniuses</em> is training for an Ontario e-sports tournament called <em>The Provincial</em>, which is 30 days away.
		They are scheduled to play at least one scrim (practice game) with another university team every day for the next 30 days; their coach tells them they will be playing a total of 42 games.
	</p>
	<p>
		Prove that there was a period of consecutive days during which the team scrimmed exactly 17 times.
    </p>
</statement>
<hint>
	<p>
		Similar to <xref ref="ex-php-shower"/>.	
	</p>
</hint>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
	<p>
		Fall 2020 course data about 1000 first-year students at a college reveal that:
		<ul>
			<li>800 are taking calculus</li>
			<li>750 are taking linear algebra</li>
			<li>550 are taking an intro to proofs course</li>
			<li>650 are taking calculus and linear algebra</li>
			<li>500 are taking linear algebra and proofs</li>
			<li>500 are taking calculus and proofs</li>
			<li>450 are taking all three</li>
		</ul>
		<ol label="(a)">
			<li>How many students are taking none of these courses? </li>
			<li>How many students are taking only linear algebra?</li>
			<li>Draw a venn diagram and indicate the number of students for each part of the diagram.</li>
		</ol>
    </p>
</statement>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
	<p>
		How many ways are there to place 11 distinct people into 3 distinct rooms?
	</p>
	<p>
		How many ways are there to place 11 distinct people into 3 distinct rooms such that each room has at least one person?
    </p>
</statement>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
	<p>
		Twenty students in a class exchange quiz papers for peer evaluation. 
		How many ways can this be done so that no student gets their own paper?
    </p>
</statement>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
	<p>
		Count the number of 5-letter arrangements that can be formed from the letters of the word
	</p>
	<sidebyside width="30%" margins="auto" halign="center">
		<p>EUPHORIA</p>
	</sidebyside>
	<p>
		such that the string EAR does not appear, and there is at least one vowel.
    </p>
</statement>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
	<p>
		Count the number of integer solutions to the system
		<me> \begin{cases} x_1 + x_2 + x_3 + x_4 = 25 \amp \\ 
			2 \leq x_1 \leq 9 \amp \\
			3 \leq x_2 \leq 9 \amp \\
			-1 \leq x_3 \leq 11 \amp \\
			5 \leq x_4 \ \ \amp \end{cases}</me>
    </p>
</statement>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
	<p>
		Count the number of <xref ref="eg-counting-lattice-path" text="custom">lattice paths</xref> from <m>(0,0)</m> to <m>(6,4)</m> that pass through <em>at least one</em> of the points <m>(2,3)</m>, <m>(3,1)</m>, and <m>(5,4)</m>.
    </p>
</statement>
</exercise>

<p>
</p>

<sidebyside width="40%" margins="auto">
<image xml:id="img-pie-lattice-path" halign="center">
	<description>A six by four grid.</description>
    <latex-image>
		\begin{tikzpicture}
		\draw[-,color=black,dashed] (0,0) grid (6,4);
		\fill[thick] (0,0) circle[radius=3pt];
		\fill[] (2,3) circle[radius=2.5pt];
		\fill[] (3,1) circle[radius=2.5pt];
		\fill[] (5,4) circle[radius=2.5pt];
		\fill[thick] (6,4) circle[radius=3pt];
		\node[label={\footnotesize$(6,4)$}] at (6.7,3.6){};
		\node[label={\footnotesize$(0,0)$}] at (-0.7,-0.4){};
		\end{tikzpicture}
	</latex-image>
</image>
</sidebyside>


<exercise>
<statement>
	<p>
		Consider a set of <m>n</m> cats and <m>n</m> dogs; suppose we want to pair them up for an afternoon playdate.
		Derive formulas for the number of ways this can be done, such that:
		<ol label="(a)">
			<li>For each <m>i</m>, the <m>i</m>th heaviest cat is <em>not</em> paired up with the <m>i</m>th heaviest dog (but pairs can have two dogs or two cats).</li>
			<li>Same condition as (a), but also each pair has exactly one cat and one dog.</li>
		</ol>
    </p>
</statement>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
	<p>
		Suppose that four friends have two pets each<mdash/>a cat and a dog<mdash/>and they all meet up at the park.
		They decide to form four groups of one human, one cat, and one dog each.
		Count the number of ways they can do this, such that:
		<ol label="(a)">
			<li>No human is with their dog.</li>
			<li>No human is with either of their pets.</li>
			<li>Each human is grouped with at most one of their pets.</li>
		</ol>
    </p>
</statement>
</exercise>



</exercises>



